{"test_questions": [[{"question": "The resolution of an n bit DAC with a maximum input of 5 V is 5 mV. The value of n is", "opta": "8", "optb": "9", "optc": "10", "optd": "11", "ans": "C", "explanation": "1000 = 5 or N = 10."}, {"question": "2's complement of binary number 0101 is", "opta": "1011", "optb": "1111", "optc": "1101", "optd": "1110", "ans": "A", "explanation": "1's complement of 0101 is 1010 and 2's complement is 1010+1 = 1011."}, {"question": "An OR gate has 4 inputs. One input is high and the other three are low. The output", "opta": "is low", "optb": "is high", "optc": "is alternately high and low", "optd": "may be high or low depending on relative magnitude of inputs", "ans": "B", "explanation": "In OR any input high means high output."}, {"question": "Decimal number 10 is equal to binary number", "opta": "1110", "optb": "1010", "optc": "1001", "optd": "1000", "ans": "B", "explanation": "1010 = 8 + 2 = 10 in decimal."}, {"question": "Both OR and AND gates can have only two inputs.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Any number of inputs are possible."}, {"question": "A device which converts BCD to seven segment is called", "opta": "encoder", "optb": "decoder", "optc": "multiplexer", "optd": "none of these", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Decoder converts binary/BCD to alphanumeric."}, {"question": "In 2's complement representation the number 11100101 represents the decimal number", "opta": "+37", "optb": "-31", "optc": "+27", "optd": "-27", "ans": "D", "explanation": "A = 11100101. Therefore A = 00011010 and A' = A + 1 = 00011011 = 16 + 8 + 2 + 1 = 27. Therefore A = -27."}, {"question": "A decade counter skips", "opta": "binary states 1000 to 1111", "optb": "binary states 0000 to 0011", "optc": "binary states 1010 to 1111", "optd": "binary states 1111 to higher", "ans": "C", "explanation": "A decade counter counts from 0 to 9. It has 4 flip-flops. The states skipped are 10 to 15 or 1010 to 1111."}, {"question": "BCD input 1000 is fed to a 7 segment display through a BCD to 7 segment decoder/driver. The segments which will lit up are", "opta": "a, b, d", "optb": "a, b, c", "optc": "all", "optd": "a, b, g, c, d", "ans": "C", "explanation": "1000 equals decimal 8 Therefore all segments will lit up."}, {"question": "A ring counter with 5 flip flops will have", "opta": "5 states", "optb": "10 states", "optc": "32 states", "optd": "infinite states", "ans": "A", "explanation": "No answer description available for this question. Let us discuss."}, {"question": "For the gate in the given figure the output will be", "opta": "0", "optb": "1", "optc": "A", "optd": "A", "ans": "D", "explanation": "If A = 0, Y = 1 and A = 1, Y = 0 Therefore Y = A."}, {"question": "In the expression A + BC, the total number of minterms will be", "opta": "2", "optb": "3", "optc": "4", "optd": "5", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The min terms are ABC + ABC + AB C + ABC + ABC."}, {"question": "The circuit in the given figure is", "opta": "positive logic OR gate", "optb": "negative logic OR gate", "optc": "negative logic AND gate", "optd": "positive logic AND gate", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Since V(1) is lower state than V(0) it is a negative logic circuit. Since diodes are in parallel, it is an OR gate."}, {"question": "Which of the following is non-saturating?", "opta": "TTL", "optb": "CMOS", "optc": "ECL", "optd": "Both (a) and (b)", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Since it is non-saturating, ECL has low propagation delay."}, {"question": "The number of digits in octal system is", "opta": "8", "optb": "7", "optc": "9", "optd": "10", "ans": "A", "explanation": "The octal system has 8 digits 0 to 7."}, {"question": "The access time of a word in 4 MB main memory is 100 ms. The access time of a word in a 32 kb data cache memory is 10 ns. The average data cache bit ratio is 0.95. The efficiency of memory access time is", "opta": "9.5 ns", "optb": "14.5 ns", "optc": "20 ns", "optd": "95 ns", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Access time = 0.95 x 10 + 0.05 x 100."}, {"question": "The expression Y = pM (0, 1, 3, 4) is", "opta": "POS", "optb": "SOP", "optc": "Hybrid", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "This is product of sums expression."}, {"question": "An 8 bit DAC has a full scale output of 2 mA and full scale error of \u00b1 0.5%. If input is 10000000 the range of outputs is", "opta": "994 to 1014 \u03bcA", "optb": "990 to 1020 \u03bcA", "optc": "800 to 1200 \u03bcA", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "10000000 = 128, 11111111 = 255 \nIf there is no error, output =  = 1004\u03bcA. \nMaximum error =  \nHence range of output 994 to 1014 \u03bcA."}, {"question": "Decimal 43 in hexadecimal and BCD number system is respectively.", "opta": "B2, 01000011", "optb": "2B, 01000011", "optc": "2B, 00110100", "optd": "B2, 01000100", "ans": "B", "explanation": "(43)10 = (2B)16\n(43)10 = (01000011)2 ."}, {"question": "The circuit of the given figure realizes the function", "opta": "Y = (A + B) C + DE", "optb": "Y = A + B + C + D + E", "optc": "AB + C +DE", "optd": "AB + C(D + E)", "ans": "A", "explanation": "or \nY = (A + B)C + DE."}, {"question": "An AND gate has two inputs A and B and one inhibit input 3, Output is 1 if", "opta": "A = 1, B = 1, S = 1", "optb": "A = 1, B = 1, S = 0", "optc": "A = 1, B = 0, S = 1", "optd": "A = 1, B = 0, S = 0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "All AND inputs must be 1 and inhibit 0 for output to be 1."}, {"question": "The greatest negative number which can be stored is 8 bit computer using 2's complement arithmetic is", "opta": "- 256", "optb": "- 128", "optc": "- 255", "optd": "- 127", "ans": "B", "explanation": "The largest negative number is 1000 0000 = -128."}, {"question": "A JK flip flop has tpd= 12 ns. The largest modulus of a ripple counter using these flip flops and operating at 10 MHz is", "opta": "16", "optb": "64", "optc": "128", "optd": "256", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Number of flip-flops =  = 8.333 say 8 \nModulus = 28 = 256."}, {"question": "The basic storage element in a digital system is", "opta": "flip flop", "optb": "counter", "optc": "multiplexer", "optd": "encoder", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Storing can be done only in memory and flip-flop is a memory element."}, {"question": "In a ripple counter,", "opta": "whenever a flip flop sets to 1, the next higher FF toggles", "optb": "whenever a flip flop sets to 0, the next higher FF remains unchanged", "optc": "whenever a flip flop sets to 1, the next higher FF faces race condition", "optd": "whenever a flip flop sets to 0, the next higher FF faces race condition", "ans": "A", "explanation": "In a ripple counter the effect ripples through the counter."}, {"question": "A 12 bit ADC is used to convert analog voltage of 0 to 10 V into digital. The resolution is", "opta": "2.44 mV", "optb": "24.4 mV", "optc": "1.2 V", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "A", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "For the truth table of the given figure Y =", "opta": "A + B + C", "optb": "A + BC", "optc": "A", "optd": "B", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Y = A B C + A B C + AB C + A B C = A B (C + C) + A B (C + C) = A B + AB = B(A + A) = B."}, {"question": "A full adder can be made out of", "opta": "two half adders", "optb": "two half adders and a OR gate", "optc": "two half adders and a NOT gate", "optd": "three half adders", "ans": "B", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "If the functions w, x, y, z are as follows.w = R + PQ + RS , x = PQR S + PQR S + PQ R SThen", "opta": "w = z x = z", "optb": "w = z, x = y", "optc": "w = y", "optd": "w = y = z", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Use k-map, then it will be easy."}, {"question": "The output of a half adder is", "opta": "SUM", "optb": "CARRY", "optc": "SUM and CARRY", "optd": "none of the above", "ans": "C", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "Minimum number of 2-input NAND gates required to implement the function F = (x + y) (Z + W) is", "opta": "3", "optb": "4", "optc": "5", "optd": "6", "ans": "B", "explanation": "F = (x + y) (z + w) = xy.(z + w)\n= xyz + xyw\n=  minimum no. of 2 input NAND gate."}, {"question": "Which device has one input and many outputs?", "opta": "Multiplexer", "optb": "Demultiplexer", "optc": "Counter", "optd": "Flip flop", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Demultiplexer takes data from one line and directs it to any of its N output depending on the status of its select lines."}, {"question": "A carry look ahead adder is frequently used for addition because", "opta": "it costs less", "optb": "it is faster", "optc": "it is more accurate", "optd": "is uses fewer gates", "ans": "B", "explanation": "In look ahead carry adder the carry is directly derived from the gates when original inputs are being added. Hence the addition is fast. This process requires more gates and is costly."}, {"question": "The counter in the given figure is", "opta": "Mod 3", "optb": "Mod 6", "optc": "Mod 8", "optd": "Mod 7", "ans": "B", "explanation": "When counter is 110 the counter resets. Hence mod 6."}, {"question": "In register index addressing mode the effective address is given by", "opta": "index register value", "optb": "sum of the index register value and the operand", "optc": "operand", "optd": "difference of the index register value and the operand", "ans": "B", "explanation": "4 = 22, in up scaling digit will be shifted by two bit in right direction."}, {"question": "7BF16 = __________ 2", "opta": "0111 1011 1110", "optb": "0111 1011 1111", "optc": "0111 1011 0111", "optd": "0111 1011 0011", "ans": "B", "explanation": "7BF16 = 7 x 162 + 11 x 161 + 15 x 160 = 1983 in decimal = 0111 1011 1111 in binary."}, {"question": "For the minterm designation Y = \u2211 m (1, 3, 5, 7) the complete expression is", "opta": "Y = A BC + A B C", "optb": "Y = A B C + A B C + ABC + A BC", "optc": "Y = A B C + A B C + ABC + A BC", "optd": "Y = A B C + ABC + A BC + A BC", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Decimal number 1 = binary number 001 = A BC Decimal number 7 = binary number 111= ABC, Decimal number 3 = binary number 011= ABC Decimal number 5 = binary number 101= ABC . Hence result."}, {"question": "Zero suppression is not used in actual practice.", "opta": "True", "optb": "False", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Zero suppression is commonly used."}, {"question": "A counter type A/D converter contains a 4 bit binary ladder and a counter driven by a 2 MHz clock. Then conversion time", "opta": "8 \u03bc sec", "optb": "10 \u03bc sec", "optc": "2 \u03bc sec", "optd": "5 \u03bc sec", "ans": "A", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "The hexadecimal number (3E8)16 is equal to decimal number", "opta": "1000", "optb": "982", "optc": "768", "optd": "323", "ans": "A", "explanation": "3 x 162 + 14 x 161 + 8 = 1000."}, {"question": "The number of distinct Boolean expression of 4 variables is", "opta": "16", "optb": "256", "optc": "1024", "optd": "65536", "ans": "D", "explanation": "22n = 224 = 216 ."}, {"question": "The fixed count that should be used so that the output register will represent the input for a 6 bit dual slope A/D converter uses a reference of -6v and a 1 MHz clock. It uses a fixed count of 40 (101000).", "opta": "000110", "optb": "0010", "optc": "1111", "optd": "011101", "ans": "A", "explanation": "If  is made to be unity, the O/P count N2 = ei,  N1 = 6 = 000110."}, {"question": "For the K map in the given figure the simplified Boolean expression is", "opta": "A C + A D + ABC", "optb": "A C + A D + ABC", "optc": "A C + A D + ACD", "optd": "A C + A D + AB C", "ans": "A", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "A memory system of size 16 k bytes is to be designed using memory chips which have 12 address lines and 4 data lines each. The number of such chips required to design the memory system is", "opta": "2", "optb": "4", "optc": "8", "optd": "18", "ans": "C", "explanation": "."}, {"question": "In a 7 segment display, LEDs b and c lit up. The decimal number displayed is", "opta": "9", "optb": "7", "optc": "3", "optd": "1", "ans": "D", "explanation": ""}, {"question": "AB + AB =", "opta": "B", "optb": "A", "optc": "1", "optd": "0", "ans": "B", "explanation": "AB + AB = A(B + B) = A . 1 = A."}, {"question": "In a BCD to 7 segment decoder the minimum and maximum number of outputs active at any time is", "opta": "2 and 7", "optb": "3 and 7", "optc": "1 and 6", "optd": "3 and 6", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Minimum number of outputs when input is decimal 1 and maximum number of outputs when input is decimal 8."}, {"question": "A three state switch has three outputs. These are", "opta": "low, low and high", "optb": "low, high, high", "optc": "low. floating, low", "optd": "low, high, floating", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Third state is floating."}, {"question": "Maxterm designation for A + B + C is", "opta": "M0", "optb": "M1", "optc": "M3", "optd": "M4", "ans": "A", "explanation": "A + B + C = 000 = M0 ."}, {"question": "1's complement of 11100110 is", "opta": "00011001", "optb": "10000001", "optc": "00011010", "optd": "00000000", "ans": "A", "explanation": "Replace 1 by 0 and 0 by 1."}]]}